Okay, calm down.
You got nervous, man.
Hello everyone and welcome to the Katie
Halper Show. So excited to be here with
you. We have an amazing show for you
today. Uh just going to get started with
it, but I have some important
announcements. But first, who are we
talking to on today's show? We will be
talking to esteemed, prolific,
unstoppable historian Gerald Horn. And
then we'll be talking to CIA
whistleblower John Kuryaku. But first,
again, some announcements. Uh please
subscribe to this channel. It's a great
way to help uh grow the show and bring
more people to the show. We've passed
90,000
subscribers, which is great, and we
couldn't have done that without you. But
let's get to 100,000. Let's get past
100,000. So again, to do that, you just
hit subscribe and then you hit the bell.
And then that way you also uh don't miss
any of our streams or any of our clips.
And what else can you do? You can also
like the video. Please do like this
video right now. Just hit the like.
That's another way to help the algorithm
so we can fight against the corporate
overlords who try to control us through
uh suppress algorithmic suppression. Uh
like any of the videos that you watch,
like it right now. Like videos that you
watch uh after the fact. Also, you can
become YouTube members and that way you
get access to uh cute badges and emojis.
So, make sure you consider that and
become Patreon supporters for just $1 a
month. That's $12 a year. You help make
the show happen. It really couldn't have
happened without your support. And if
you can afford to become Patreon
supporters at the $5 a month level, you
get amazing extended interviews and
bonus interviews. So, for instance, on
tonight's show, uh if you're watching
live, you're in luck. you'll be able to
see the full interview with John
Kuryaku. But if you're watching later in
order to see the full interview with
John Kuryaku, then you'll have to go to
patreon.com/thekatyhelper
show. Again, that's
show. And there are other interviews
that we don't play at all during the
live streams. And uh you have access to
that again at patreon.com/thekatyateler
show at the $5 level. And thank you so
much to everyone who already is a
Patreon member at either level.
Um, I'll be speaking to Michael Hudson
and Richard Wolf, and those will be
mostly Patreon only, so it's definitely
worth uh your while. Now, another
announcement. We have some great news.
So, as people probably know, I started a
petition for Roger Waters right to
perform in Frankfurt. Uh, Frankfurt had
uh cancelled one of his concerts, a May
28th concert, because they smeared him
as an anti-semite uh over his support of
Palestinian human rights and over his
criticism of Israel. So, we launched a
petition demanding they reverse their
decision. A lot of you signed it. Over
35,000 people signed it. Also, uh Roger
Waters challenged them in court. And an
amazing news guys
read uh quoting Deutsche, an
administrative court in the German city
of Frankfurt on Monday found that
neither the city nor the state of Hess
had the right to cancel a Roger Waters
concert at the Frankfurt Fest Hall as it
had previously sought to do. The court
said that as the owners of concert
organizer Messi Frankfurt, the state and
city were obliged to quote make it
possible for Waters to stage the concert
end quote as contractually agreed. So,
yay, good news. And more good news uh
about another guest of the show and
friend of the show, Laura Shehy, who I
had on a couple months ago. She's the
assistant professor of clinical
psychology at George Washington who had
been smeared as an anti-semite by uh the
right-wing pro-Israel group Stand with
Us. And she's been fully exonerated by a
third party investigation. So, we got
two victories that we can be excited
about. Um, so I think that's all the
announcements I'm going to make. I'm
just going to get the show rolling
because I know you guys are very excited
about tonight's guests. Uh, we're going
to bring on the extremely prolific
historian Gerald Horn, who holds the
Moors Professorship of History and
African-American Studies at the
University of Houston. His research has
addressed issues of race in a variety of
relations involving labor, politics,
civil rights, and war. He is the author
of over 40 books, the latest of which is
the counterrevolution of 1836, Texas,
Slavery, and Jim Crow, and the roots of
US fascism. So, welcome, Dr. Horn.
Thank you for inviting me. of course. So
excited to have you back on the show.
Always learn so much from talking to
you. We're going to be talking about
this uh very scary indictment of four US
citizens who are accused of being uh
illegal agents of the Russian
government. But before we get to that, I
want to talk to you about what is
happening in Sudan. Um as people
probably know, um 459 civilians at least
have died since fighting uh broke out on
April 15th. But what is happening there?
Why is it happening there? And what is
the role of the West in this conflict?
Well, as you may know, in the 1980s, in
a previous career as a left-wing lawyer,
I was brought by the Union of Arab
Jurists to engage in shuttle diplomacy
with regard to the then percolating
civil war between Sudan and what became
South Sudan about a decade ago when it
successfully declared independence. But
in order to understand what's happening
in Sudan, you have to go back to
independence in the mid 1950s when Sudan
had an exceedingly strong communist
party, perhaps the second strongest on
the continent behind South Africa that
was enmical to US cold war interests
which then began to destabilize the
country and like a seessaw that led to
the rise of military forces ruling in
cartoon not to mention religious zealots
the latter of whom included the
notorious Osama bin Laden.
who was housed there in the 1990s
according to the US CIA at least and Mr.
Clinton then fighting sex scandals lob
cruise missiles at cartoon supposedly to
destroy Mr. bin Laden and his forces but
actually destroying manufacturing
facilities. But in terms of the present
crisis, it stems from an intercent
conflict within the military. That is to
say, as many of your audience may know,
the Sudin military versus a wing of the
Sudin military. It would be as if the
Pentagon was fighting the Navy Seals and
the Green Berets. But there are economic
issues as well. The Sudin military no
doubt would like to ape the military in
neighboring Egypt which controls a good
deal of the economy uh in Cairo. Uh the
so-called rapid support forces which are
fighting the Sudin military are backed
by the Gulf Arabs, United Arab Emirates.
The rapid support forces have sent young
men to their deaths in the losing war in
Yemen uh which is backed as you know by
the Saudis. The Sudin military is backed
by the Egyptian military. The United
States is very upset because uh the
Vagner group of Russia has established
close ties to Sudan's neighbor. Speaking
of the Central African Republic, the
Russians, we are told, are establishing
a military base in Port Sudan on the Red
Sea due south of that major choke point
that is the Suez Canal. And we know that
the United States supposedly is
withdrawing a number of its diplomats
and US nationals from its base in
Djibouti due east. But there is concern
that that might lead to a disguised
intervention of sorts by Uncle Sam.
Wow. Okay. Um what do you think is uh
concerning the United States in this
conflict?
Well, they're concerned about Russia. It
also they're also concerned that France
cannot keep a lid on its neoc colonial
empire. That's been the de facto
arrangement between Paris and Washington
going back to the Suez debacle of 1956
when you'll recall that Britain, France,
and Israel attacked Egypt for control of
the Suez Canal. After that fiasco,
London decided to tie its apron strings
closer to Uncle Sam. Uh France went in a
different direction. Washington said,
"Fine, but you ought to be able to keep
a lid on this neoc colonial empire."
That is not happening. You know that the
French have been ousted from Mali.
They're in bad odor in Borina Faso. That
is having knock-on effects with regard
to the European Union and neighboring
Chad due west of Sudan. You see that
relations are broken down between Berlin
and and Jamaa. So Washington is probably
concerned that it needs to elbow France
aside since it can no longer play its
neoc colonial role. That is not
necessarily winning friends and
influencing people in France. Recall
that Mr. Mcronone just a few days ago
raised questions about whether France
and the European Union would be on board
with this new cold war against China. So
this is a very complicated situation in
Sudan that has repercussions both uh
continentally in Africa and globally.
Uh Vice President Kla Harris recently
went to Africa and she was asked a lot
by the media about what uh the United
States was going to do to stop China
from interfering in Africa. Uh what are
your thoughts on this framing? Well,
what's curious about Vice President
Harris's trip to the continent is that
every airport she landed in Acra Ghana,
Lusaka, Zambia, Dar Salam, Tanzania, the
airports were either partially or wholly
funded and or designed by Chinese
interests. And so the Africans listened
politely and courteously, but it would
not be in their best interest to tag
along after Uncle Sam with regard to
this latest escapade. a new cold war
that can only be to the detriment of
African interests.
And what is your what are your thoughts
on the role of China in Africa?
Well, it's complicated. I think the
question is what do Africans think?
They're they're mostly in favor because
if China was not there, that would give
France and Uncle Sam and London and the
traditional powers more leeway to force
unwanted proposals down Africans
throats. The Africans want a
counterveilling force and China plays
that role. Not to mention helping to
build infrastructure. Be it a a railway
from Nairobi, Kenya, the capital, to the
Indian Ocean coast city of Mombasa, or a
railway from Adis Ababa, Ethiopia, the
second most populous nation on the
African continent due east to Djibouti,
which is now the major port for Adis
Ababa for Ethiopia since the country is
virtually landlocked and not to mention
the African Union headquarters itself in
Adis Ababa, Ethiopia. So uh generally
speaking the Africans say thumbs up with
regard to China because the alternative
would be uh the European powers and
North Atlantic uh nations generally
running roughshot over their sovereign
interests.
Um and what do you think of this? It
seems like there is perhaps
consideration uh of a more multi-olar
world. Uh you I heard during an
interview refer to this you mentioned
Macron sounding somewhat interested in
this. Uh what are your what are your
predictions?
Well I think it's already in motion. Uh
you need only look at the hysteria in
Washington. Bipartisan hysteria by the
way concerning China. It's very
dangerous. You know that US military
forces just engaged in major military
maneuvers off the coast of South China
with their Filipino comrades. Imagine if
China had been engaged in
maneuvers off the coast of Los Angeles
or San Francisco, let us say with the
Cuban forces, for example, uh you would
have people in Washington running around
with their hair on fire. So
multipolarizing
and a multipolar world is I think
already in motion. The only question is
to what extent will it go? Will it lead
to ddollarization? that is to say the
increasing
uh lack of use of the dollar and
international trade. You already see
that with regard to China and Saudi
Arabia given President Xi's visit to
that earthwall US ally just a few months
ago. You see it in the trade between
Russia and China in wake of the uh
Ukrainian uh intervention by NATO and
then of the special military operation
of Russia. So multi-polarizing
is already with us. The only question is
to what depths will it go.
Um we're going to go back to uh more uh
foreign policy questions and also uh US
politics questions. But I also want to
bring up this news uh that people
probably know. Legendary singer, actor
and activist Harry Bellfonte has died at
the age of 96.
Uh what should people know about him and
what his historical significance is?
His historic significance is profound.
Uh to quote the title of a popular 19th
century US novel to a certain extent he
was the last of the Moheagans. What I
mean by that is that Harry Bellafonte
established organic ties with the US
left. He confessed openly that Paul
Robson, the late artist, actor and
activist who
about who you've of course written the
book.
Yes. Who was persecuted by the US
authorities and in fact this ties into
the coming story we're going to discuss
about the indictment of the African
People's Socialist Party. That is to say
that Paul Robinson touched a red line
when he cast doubt in 1949 as to whether
black Americans would be on board with
regard to a nuclear war with Moscow.
Paul Robson crossed a red line when he
was involved in a petition to the United
Nations charging United States with
genocide against black people that led
to the snatching of its passport. His
income plummets from the six figures to
the four figures. All that time Paul
Paul Robersonson was accompanied by a
young Harry Bellafonte and to an extent
I should add as well by Sydney Portier
who was Harry's longtime long-term
friend and comrade and then Harry
Bellafonte after he became wildly
popular one of the uh best-selling
musical artists in the history of the
industry in this United States he began
to fund and subsidize subsidize the
movement of Dr. King. Uh, in fact, if
you want to understand how Dr. King in
his 20s and 30s could zip around the
country and around the world, you need
to look no further than Harry
Bellfonte's checkbook. So, when he
passes, which he did today, it's an
enormous loss. It's a like a a sequoia
that's collap collapsed in the forest.
Yeah. I just wanted to share this um an
image. Uh there are a lot of famous
images of him and of Dr. King and Harry
Bellfonte. I'm just uh bringing one up.
Let's on a somewhat related note because
we're talking about black radicals and
the left and uh also persecution,
political persecution. Of course, I want
to ask you about this other story that I
uh refer to in the introduction. Uh the
justice department has indicted four US
citizens and three Russians charged with
conspiring to use US citizens as quote
illegal agents of the Russian
government. Uh the US citizens were
members of the African People's
Socialist Party and I'm just going to
share what the African People's
Socialist Party says about itself as an
organization. The aims and objectives of
the APSUSA are to lead the struggle of
the African workingclass and oppressed
masses against US capitalist colonialist
domination and all the manifestations of
oppression and exploitation that result
from this relationship. The party
recognizes that the particular character
of the oppression of African people
within US borders is domestic or
internal colonialism. Leading the
struggle to end the system of domestic
colonialism and smash the US capitalist
colonial state is the immediate task of
the African people's socialist party USA
and the African working class in the US.
We're going uh so we're going to and
we're going to get into the more of the
substance of the indictment during the
second half of the show when I talk to
John Kuryaku. But I wanted to ask you
about the history of black radicals
being presented as foreign assets,
especially uh Russian assets.
Well, obviously the African People's
Socialist Party, like Paul Robson, has
crossed the red line by apparently
having relations with Moscow. I've
already mentioned the unfortunate case
of Paul Robson himself, but his comrade
Webb Dubo, a founder of the NAACP, a
founder of pan-Africanism, was indicted
by the US authorities in federal court
supposedly for being an agent of Moscow
because he led a campaign to ban nuclear
weapons. Banning nuclear weapons was
thought to be an idea that came straight
from the then Soviet Union. In other
words, one, as a black person, A, you
were not allowed to have that kind of
relationship with a major power that had
contradictions with Washington. And B,
generally speaking, you should steer
clear of foreign policy, which is a
dictim, I'm afraid to say, that's still
being followed by a goodly number of our
organizations. The NAACP has barely
gotten involved in foreign policy since
Dubo was indicted. or if they have
gotten involved has been on the wrong
side with regard to, for example, the
pro-Vietnam war sentiment that
percolated through the NAACP in the
1960s and 70s. And this is nothing new.
If you go back to the founding of the
United States in 1776, it's no secret to
historians at least that black people by
several orders of magnitude did not
engage in class collaboration and stand
alongside slave owners like George
Washington and Thomas Jefferson and
James Madison. uh they generally stood
alongside London. That followed during
the War of 1812 when black people helped
to torch the White House, sending James
Madison, the president, and his geralous
spouse, Dolly, fleeing into the streets,
one step ahead of the Posi, with the
black people then fleeing on British
ships to Trinidad and Tobago, where
their descendants continued to reside.
In the 20th century, you saw black
people at the time when Whitro Wilson,
the then US president in the first uh
two decades of the 20th century, uh he
sent US troops into Mexico in order to
try to ensnare Ponchovilla. At that
time, you had black people in solidarity
with Ponchovilla. And so, this has been
a repetitive pattern. And I think that
there's a certain kind of paranoia about
the black community. There's the fear
that because we are so maltreated and
mistreated that our ears will perk up
whenever a foreign p policy excuse me
whenever a foreign power uh beckons in
our direction. And I think that that is
the underlying force if you like behind
the indictment of the African people's
socialist party.
Yeah. And it seems like uh it's
extremely infantilizing also, right?
Because it's the the idea is that uh
these people like Omali Yeshella who's
been involved in activism for decades.
Uh he's 80 I believe 80 or 81 years old.
Uh the idea that he can't have his own
political ideas that he has to be doing
this at the behest of a foreign
government. uh like his own critique of
NATO can't be something that he comes up
with on his own is very offensive.
Well, if you'll recall during the cold
war, if Moscow took a certain position
and you had a similar position, uh ipso
facto that meant that you were an agent
of Moscow. It it got to the level
absurdity. I'm saying this in order to
illustrate the absurdity. That is to say
that if Moscow was in favor of fighting
tooth decay and you were in favor of
fighting tooth decay, that might mean
that you're an agent of Moscow.
And that, as I said, I think to to
understand this strange phenomenon, you
really have to understand a the historic
mil malreatment and mistreatment of
black people, which then leads to
paranoia that we will then ally with
foreign power powers. And of course we
have allied powers.
But it seems to me the answer is to
reduce if not eliminate the maltreatment
and mistreatment. And then you don't
have to be tossing out uh indictments
against black organizations like you're
tossing out confetti for example.
Right. Um
and can you talk a bit about this
tradition of black uh inter
internationalism?
Well, certainly uh if I'm not mistaken,
uh Chairman Omali himself was involved
in the San Francisco Bay area with the
Black Panther Party and they are usually
exhibit A when it comes to
internationalism. Recall that they
established a legation, a diplomatic
mission in North Africa and Algeria.
At a time when Congo Brazville was known
as the People's Republic of the Congo
and was ruled by pro-socialist elements,
they sent delegations there. The Black
Panther Party sent delegations to North
Korea uh to Vietnam when the United
States was involved in a shooting war
with Vietnam. And in fact, the Black
Panthers offered to organize battalions
to go fight alongside the the
Vietnamese. And indeed uh this too got
them into quite a bit of hot water
helping to explain why they were
pulverized so severely up to and
including uh leaders such as Mark Clark
and Fred Hampton being shot in their
beds in December 1969 by officers of the
state. So this question of black
alignment on with the real or imagined
antagonist in the United States it's a
very serious issue. It's really one of
the most powerful tools that the black
community has. But alas, because you
tend to be se severely punished if you
use that tool, most decide to stay away
from that tool.
Um, I wanted to share some clips of uh
modern day because it's of course not
just a historical phenomenon. we're
seeing this indictment today, but also
some other examples of uh people
suggesting that projects of black
liberation are actually Russian ops. So,
uh let's take a look at what Kla Harris
had to say uh and the Breakfast Club
about Colin Kaepernick's uh protest.
So, that's what they start to do,
right? That's what they start to do.
They did it then, they will do it now.
You know, people have said if you look
at, for example, the whole remember the
whole the heat that ended up around the
bend the knee and Colin Kaepernick,
many smart people have said it actually
was not a thing.
Mhm.
The Russian bots started taking that on.
Really?
Yes.
You feel like you're being targeted by
Russian bots now?
Well, we already know we are. Yeah.
So,
any thoughts on that? I have another
clip, too. But
I'm not sure I heard correctly. Was Vice
President Harris suggesting
that Russian bots were promoting Colin
Kaepernick, the former San Francisco
49ers quarterback who a few years ago
began to protest police terror against
black people by kneeling on the grid
iron, which to this very day has led to
his being quote black ballalled unquote
by the National Football League. Was
that the import of what she was seeing?
Yeah.
Well, I'm sure Vice President Harris is
sufficiently intelligent to know better.
After all, she was in the San Francisco
Bay area when these protests erupted. I
assume she was reading the newspapers.
As a matter of fact, as district
attorney of San Francisco, she was
involved in a number of controversial
cases where the San Francisco Police
Department should have been brought to
account uh with regard to uh
mistreatment and maltreatment of black
citizens and were not. In fact, she's
probably familiar with the uh Oakland
based attorney uh John Barers who's made
a pretty penny uh suing the San
Francisco Police Department, including
uh during her administration. So, it's
disappointing if that is the import of
what Vice President Harris was saying
then.
Well, yes, and and it's uh certainly a
trendy thing to say because here's Susan
Rice. Uh we have a clip of Susan Rice
talking to Wolf Blitzer. Uh people
probably know although this is uh
there's some uh breaking news. She is
stepping down uh from her role as a uh
domestic policy adviser for Biden, but
she of course was before that national
security adviser and ambassador to the
United Nations under President Barack
Obama. And here she is talking about the
George Floyd protests.
Uh and they probably also
bet based on my experience, I'm not
reading the intelligence uh today uh or
these days, but based on my experience,
this is right out of the Russian
playbook as well. The Russian playbook
as well. But we can't allow the
extremists, the foreign actors to
distract from the real problems we have
in this country that are longstanding,
centuries old, and need to be addressed
responsibly by new leadership.
You're you're absolutely right. on the
uh foreign interference because we know
for decades the Russians uh when it was
the Soviet Union, the communists,
they've often often tied tried to
embarrass the United States by promoting
the the racial divide in our country.
But what you're suggesting, ambassador,
is that they're still trying to do that.
Is that what you're saying?
Well, we see it all the time. We've seen
it for years and and frankly every day
on social media where they take uh any
divisive, painful issue, whether it's
immigration, whether it's gay rights,
whether it's gun violence, and always
racism, and they play on both sides.
Their aim is not simply to embarrass the
United States Wolf. Their aim is to
divide us, to cause us to come into
combat with each other, to disintegrate
from within. And I would not be
surprised to learn that they have
fuamented some of these extremists on
both sides using social media. I
wouldn't be surprised to learn uh that
they're funding it in some way, shape,
or form.
Well, all I can say is physician hill
thyself. As you know more than most, the
United States has this National
Endowment for Democracy so-called which
interferes in the internal affairs of
over 190 different countries oftentimes
trying to stir unrest. And so obviously
Susan Rice knows about that particular
tool since I'm sure as US ambassador to
United Nations she was receiving
briefings about it. But as you also
probably know, this idea of blaming
Moscow, I think has in a sense come into
a roadblock. You may know that the
former acting director of the Central
Intelligence Agency, um, Mr. Morell has
said that when during the 2020 campaign
there was this controversy involving the
laptop of Hunter Biden, the vice
president's the then vice president or
excuse me the then presidential nominee
Mr. Biden's troublesome that they put
out this story with four dozen plus
intelligence agents saying that it was
probably not uh an accurate story that
it was result of Russians agents
disinformation etc. He threw Anthony
Blinkin the current secretary of state
under the bus by saying that it was
Anthony Blinkin's idea. I don't think
we've heard the last of of this story.
And I think that this question of
pointing the finger at Moscow whenever
there is an issue domestically, uh, the
chickens might be in the process of
coming home to roost.
How so?
Well, I don't think that we've heard the
last of this Hunter Biden laptop story.
Mr. Biden has just announced for
reelection. Uh, I'm sure that not only
will Fox media seek to recuperate after
sacking Tucker Carlson by outstripping
Newsmax, Newsmax and One America News in
terms of promoting this story. The Wall
Street Journal, I'm sure, will pick it
up. They've already had columns about it
for for example. So maybe that'll cause
many in the US electorate to rethink
this idea that whenever there is a
domestic issue that Moscow is
responsible and in any case as you
suggested a moment or two ago. Uh it
reminds us of what happened during the
anti-Jim Crow era whenever there was
unrest in the black community. Outside
agitators were blamed. Oftentimes the
outside agitators were traced to
connections in Moscow. In fact, Dr. King
himself was accused of being an agent of
Moscow. Uh, so I'm surprised that that
tactic is still being used because you
would think it's terribly moaten by now.
Yeah. Sadly, sadly, I guess it's still
it's it's motheaten and used at the same
time.
Well, yes, it must be effective. Uh,
otherwise it would not be used. But a as
I was suggesting a moment or two ago,
this indictment against the African
People's Socialist Party has to be taken
quite seriously. I've been urging in
other uh media appearances that the
NAACP and the NAACP legal defense fund,
not to mention the American Civil
Liberties Union and of course the
National Lawyers Guild leaked to their
defense. I know that any organization
that has socialists in its name will not
necessarily be embraced by many liberal
forces and many centrist forces. But
what needs to be understood and
recognized is that just as Dr. Dubo's
indictment in 1951
was just a president that helped to give
fuel to an overall McCarthyism and
overall red scare that eventually ins
snared many in Hollywood and snared many
in the academy. I would hope that what's
happening right now as we speak to the
African people's socialist party does
not have a similar president that's in
the process of being established.
Right. I mean, liberals won't say
anything because uh they for a couple of
reasons, but one is that I think they
probably uh just believe whatever they
hear about Russia and Russians. Uh they
also uh I think if Trump did something
like this to his enemies, people would
accuse him of fascism, but because it's
Biden doing something like this, they
won't. And what's really pathetic is
that the only remotely corporate or
mainstream media that has covered this
story was uh Tucker Carlson because
Glenn Greenwald brought it up on his
show. Obviously, leftist outlets have
been, but it hasn't penetrated, you
know, MSNBC hasn't talked about it. CNN
hasn't talked about I'm sure if they did
talk about it, they'd talk about it from
the same perspective as the Justice
Department. In other words, it would be
a story about um catching bad guys as
opposed to a story about the
criminalization of disscent and speech.
Well, fortunately, we have the Katie
Halper show which is giving this story
ventilation. And that's one of the
reasons why I would urge and encourage
your audience to give this show a like,
to go on Patreon and make a
contribution. Uh because right now we're
in very desperate straits in in this
country with a new cold war brewing with
China with forces on the left like the
African People's Socialist Party being
indicted. Uh if we do not speak up now,
I'm afraid to imagine where we will be
this time next year.
Are you surprised by this division over
Russia and China? I mean, I I've brought
this up with a bunch of guests, but I
feel like a lot of people who I usually
agree with on politics. Um,
when it comes to this issue of the uh
proxy war in Ukraine, there's uh more
people, I would say, are susceptible to
this kind of cold war 2.0 than I would
have expected.
Well, let me add a footnote. I think
that in the wake of the Putin Xi summit,
in the wake of the Xi Mcronone summit,
in the wake of the Xi Lula of Brazil
summit, I've detected that certain
forces on the left, which before all of
these summits were supportive of the
NATO escapade in Ukraine, either are
silent or are rethinking because I think
that they've come to realize that
Ukraine is chapter one. Taiwan is
chapter two and the overall question is
maintaining US hedgeimonyy in the face
of a stiff challenge from the people's
republic of China which is a juggernaut
in the passing lane. And I think that
many forces on the left have enough good
sense and common sense not to go along
with that kind of new cold war, which is
why they're either a being silent or b
rethinking their position.
I hope so. Uh tell us about your latest
book, Dr. Horn, which I highly
recommend. Well, my latest book is on
Texas and the roots of US fascism
because Texas right now, which is where
I'm speaking from. I don't think many in
your audience would believe some of the
things that are happening here. I mean,
countless numbers dying along the
border, uh, counties considering
shutting down public libraries because
they don't feel that they're able to
withdraw books they object to from the
public libraries. So, they're thinking
about shutting down the public
libraries. a throwback to what happened
during the Jim Crow era where rather
than go through desegregation, you had
counties shutting down swimming pools or
in Virginia, you had in certain counties
shutting down public schools and then
subsidizing white kids going to
privatemies through taxpayers money. Uh
this is the sort of thing that's
unfolding in the second most populous
state in the United States of America.
In some ways, Texas makes Florida under
Governor DeSantis seem progressive. And
so, what I'm trying to do in this book
is give the historical background that
has led up to this point. And if if I
may, in a few days, my next book will
drop a revolting capital, racism and
radicalism in Washington DC, 1900 to
2000. It's ironic that the capital of a
state that for the longest was an
aparate state had a black majority. And
so I'm trying to explain that uh the
ramifications of it particularly since
black people were more susceptible to
being influenced by people like Paul
Robson and Web Dubo and people of the
left. the kind of contradictions that
created particularly when African and
Caribbean diplomats started streaming
into Washington the 1950s and 1960s and
were mistaken quote unquote for black
Americans which was not winning United
States many friends and the
international community and how then
that created pressure for the overall
retreat of Jim Crow.
Wow. And that's coming out when?
In a few days.
Wow. Do you ever do anything besides
write and reads
I guess? Yeah,
of course. Of as a matter of fact, I'm
mourning.
I'm in serious mourning about the fact
that uh Netflix is stopping its DVD mail
service because people think everything
is streaming. That's false.
There are all sorts of movies and
documentaries. I'm not sure what's going
to happen to them quite frankly. And uh
I spent a lot of time actually watching
this kind of documentaries and other
movies from all over the world through
the DVD service which is disappearing on
September 30th.
Wow. What's some recent ones that you
recommend?
Well, I just saw this I just saw this
doc I can only talk about what I've seen
recently because I see so many they're
difficult to distinguish. I just saw
this 4-hour documentary on an US
aircraft carrier, the Nem. It's like a
fly onthe-wall documentary dealing with
these 5,000 plus US sailors living in
close quarters. The racial conflicts,
the gender conflicts, the looming war
that they're about to be embraced,
excuse me, about to be involved in it.
It was quite fascinating. It comes out
of PBS. It's called Carrier.
Wow. Okay. Carrier. Um, and someone in
the comments asked about your another
book of yours, one that I haven't read,
but I actually really want to. um
because he thought it was relevant to
our discussion. Uh Class Struggle in
Hollywood 1930 to 1950, Moguls,
mobsters, stars, breads, and trade
unionists. What uh can you tell us about
that book?
That book came out a few decades ago
when I was living in Southern
California, and uh it deals with labor
history uh in the film industry. Uh it's
no accident that Hollywood has produced
some of the our most stalwart leftists.
Recall that Paul Robson himself was an
actor. Harry Bellafonte was an actor. If
you look at screenwriters like Daltton
Trumbo, who wrote the screenplay to
Spartacus,
one of the most powerful anti-slavery
films ever produced, he was also a funer
of the Black Panther Party, for example,
and was also one of the celebrated
Hollywood 10, that is to say, the
screenwriters and directors who were
quote blacklisted unquote because of
their politics. And so this book, Class
Struggle in Hollywood, deals with
strikes and labor unrest in Hollywood by
below the line workers, as they're
called, painters, set decorators, uh,
etc. And of course, as you know, the
writers in Hollywood as we speak are
about to be on the picket line because
they're really being cheated royally by
the studios and they're raising their
voices and good for them.
Well, I Well, I'm going to have to read
that book. Um, and anything else that
you want to tell us about that you're
working on or any final thoughts because
you've been so generous with your time.
Well, you may have inferred reasonably
that I'm working on a book on the Black
Panther Party right now and I'm probably
going to write it by the end of the year
and it's it'll probably be be out next
year. It's dealing with the Black
Panther Party in Southern California. So
therefore, I'm dealing with Dalton
Trumbo.
They got a lot of funding from
Hollywood. Jane Fonda, for example, her
then husband uh Tom Hayden for example,
Bert Snder a who produced this powerful
anti-war documentary about the Vietnam
War was probably the major funer
of the Black Panther Party for example.
So that all that will be in this next
book and of course it'll deal with the
Angela Davis case since she comes out of
UCLA as you know was fired because of
being a member of the Communist Party
and then is arrested was facing the
death penalty for supposedly being
implicated in a courthouse shootout
about 50 odd years ago. So it's a large
cast and I'm looking forward to writing
it.
Great. How do you uh what's your writing
process? Like your work process, do you
uh work during certain hours? Do you
like do any methods like what the
Pomodoro method where you work for half
an hour and you take five minutes off or
something?
Well, when I'm in writing mode, and I'm
really not in writing mode right now.
I'm in research mode. But when I'm in
writing mode, I'll usually write four or
five days a week. I usually have music
on. Um, I even even have uh Katie Halper
on because it it tends to stimulate my
brain to hear people talking. I know
some people get distracted.
Yeah, I can't do that. Yeah.
Yeah. So, uh, that's my usual mode. And
a good day, I would say, is writing
seven to 10 pages.
Okay. Got it. Wow. That's so fascinating
that you can listen to other people
talking while you're writing. I can't at
all. I can listen to music, but it has
to be music I know so it's familiar.
Mhm. So,
well, not only do I listen to it,
sometimes if you come up with a a nice
metaphor, it'll go into my text.
Oh, great. All right. I'm gonna have to
be more poetic and inspire me. And I did
not pay Dr. Horn to say any of this, by
the way. Either this or or about why
people should support my Patreon. Purely
organic.
Absolutely.
So, don't indict him, anyone.
Really, please don't put those bad vibes
out here.
Yeah. Yeah. I shouldn't. Yeah. Well,
thank you so much and I'm really looking
forward to your next book and of course
we always love having you on. So looking
forward to talking to you again.
Thank you for inviting me.
Of course. Thank you. Have a great
night. And that was the prolific,
legendary Dr. Gerald Horn. Everyone
should get his books. I have one of them
behind me. It's the big fat red one.
That's his counterrevolution book uh
about Texas. Uh he's written uh great
books about the uh counterrevolution of
1776. That's a really great one. Uh a
really great one about boxing that I
really enjoyed. And you know, I'm not
really into sports, so it's it's so
fascinating. Thank you, Cloud, for that
super chat. Um also, I forgot to
announce in the opening that we're going
to be doing a call-in right after the
show. So, right after the show, come on
over to the call-in and we'll have a fun
chat. I'm going to bring on to the stage
someone who's been on the show before
and he's an amazing guest and amazing
storyteller. Uh John Kuryaku is the only
person to go to prison over the CIA
torture program which he blew the
whistle on. He's a former CIA analyst
and case officer, a PENUSA award winner
and best-selling author. And he's the
host co-host of Political Misfits and
writes at johncuryaku.substack.com.
So welcome John.
Oh, you're muted.
Yep. Thank you so much. Good to be back.
Thank you for coming. Everyone's very
excited to have you on.
Pleasure is mine. Thank you.
Um, so much to talk about. Let's start
off with that story that I talked about
with Professor Horn, the um indictment
of uh three Russian citizens and four US
citizens who have been uh accused of uh
and I I quote, weaponizing free speech.
Russia's foreign intelligence service
allegedly weaponize our First Amendment
rights, freedoms Russia denies its own
citizens to divide Americans and
interfere in intellect in elections in
the United States, said Assistant
Attorney General Matthew G. Olsen of the
Justice Department's National Security
Division. So that's what apparently
Russia is doing. They are weaponizing
our First Amendment rights,
right? which kind of sounds like uh
you're uh criminalizing the First
Amendment, United States Justice
Department.
Crazy. It says also in this indictment
um today's announcement paints a
harrowing picture of Russian government
actions and the lengths to which the FSB
will go to interfere with our elections,
seow discord in our nation, and
ultimately recruit US citizens to their
efforts. Uh you know what? In the
interest of transparency, um I have a I
have a show every day from 12 to two on
Sputnik Radio and I didn't approach uh
the Russians to to work at Sputnik. They
approached me and I turned them down.
This was in uh oh very early 2017. And
about six months later, they came back
and they said, "We'd really like to give
you your own show on Sputnik Radio." And
I said, "Well, listen. If I do a show
like this, I want I would want the
freedom to say anything that I want and
to criticize anybody that I want,
including Vladimir Putin, if it were to
come to that. And they said, "Done." And
I said, "Really? You are you willing to
put that in writing? Like put it in the
contract? Done." And they did. And just
as an example, on the day that Russian
forces crossed the border into Ukraine,
I said, "I unreservedly condemn the
Russian invasion of Ukraine, and I would
hope that the Russians would withdraw
their troops immediately." And then we
got along with the show.
So if if the FBI wants to talk about
criminalizing free speech, maybe we
should look instead at the Espionage Act
and the way it's used as a cudgel to to
beat people down who want to exercise
free speech by calling out government
waste, fraud, abuse, or illegalities,
but they don't want to have that
conversation.
Right. Right. Yeah. I mean, it's it's
just insane because it's basically the
allegation is that um these people are
uh
doing these things, making the position,
taking the positions that they're
taking, making the speeches that they're
taking, not because they believe in it,
not because they have decadesl long
histories of being radicals and uh
pan-Africanists and internationalists,
but because they're being paid by the
Russians.
Right. Right. And anything, the other
thing that's so ridiculous about this is
that anything that is critical of the US
will definitionally be in the best
interest of the Russian government, just
like anything that's critical of the
Russian government will definitionally
be in the best interest of the US. So
anyone who's critical of the United
States by that definition
is is a Russian asset.
It's hilarious, isn't it? And it's
ridiculous at the same time. And let's
let's look at exactly what this uh this
allegation is. This is this is what's
called a process crime, right? It's an
administrative felony. And if you look
at the sentencing guidelines that are
posted on the Justice Department's
website, conviction for committing this
crime, failure to register as a foreign
agent, the recommended sentence is 0 to
6 months in a minimum security work
camp. It's not even worth prosecuting.
You know, you have to ask, is is our
country going to be safer by prosecuting
this crime? Is society going to be
better? Are we going to be a better and
stronger country by locking these people
up because they they neglected to go to
the Justice Department's website to fill
out a form? That's what this crime is.
The allegation is that these people
didn't go to the Justice Department's
website to fill out a form. You know,
Katie, about 15 years ago, I was hired
on a short-term contract by the US Abu
Dhabi Chamber of Commerce. They hired me
to write four op-eds. So, I wrote four
op-eds, 700 words a piece, and I had to
go to the Justice Department's website
to the the Foreign uh Agents
Registration Act, FAR, website, and I
said, "My name's John Kiryaku, and
here's my address, and here's my phone
number, and I accepted X amount of money
to write four op-eds." And then you
attach the op-eds. Okay, that's it. Did
it really matter? Did anybody I won't
even ask if anybody ever read my opeds.
Did anybody ever bother to read the form
that I filled out?
And and so you're going to tell us that
these people endangered American society
and endangered American politics because
they had an opinion that didn't fit in
nice and neatly with the with the
Justice Department's opinion on whatever
issue. And so we're going to prosecute
them on felony charges. This is
outrageous.
It's a waste of resources.
And Omali Yeshella is 81 years old, by
the way.
Yeah. Exactly. Exactly.
It's just so funny because it's they're
they're trying to present Russia as
authoritarian. And what are they doing
here with literal speech and disscent?
Well, you know, and I'll give you
another example. uh Maria Bhina, who was
in the news a couple of years ago, um
she was convicted of violating this same
law, failure to register as a foreign
agent. And again, that uh that uh
sentencing guideline is 0 to 6 months.
Not only did she get 18 months
for failing to register, but she spent
the entire 18 months in solitary
confinement.
And then we are outraged when the
Republicans Republicans sorry Freudian
when the Russians arrest an American
citizen and hold them on similarly silly
and often times trumped up charges which
is what these are
right. Um as someone who obviously
served prison um time what what do you
want people to know about that
experience especially as we're talking
about people who are facing prison time
now? Wow. Where do you even begin? The
the US uh prison system at every level,
at the federal level, the state level,
and local levels, is utterly and
completely broken. I did a piece just a
week ago for Consortium News in which I
went over um just as a a random sampling
um uh 15 or 20 prison guards that have
been arrested in the last two years.
About a third of them have been arrested
for raping prisoners, both female and
male. The other twothirds have been
arrested for smuggling into prisons cell
phones and drugs, in many cases hard
drugs that ended up killing prisoners
that they were selling the drugs too. Uh
the system is completely
broken. You know, there's a book that
was written by Dr. Peter Moscows of um
John J. College School of Criminal
Justice. It's called In Defense of
Flogging, which is kind of a
tongue-in-cheek title, but he makes a
conclusion that I think is very, very
important in this book. He says that at
the federal level, the Federal Bureau of
Prisons really is nothing more than an
employment agency for otherwise
unemployable,
undereducated
rural white men. These are guys who
couldn't make it in the military. These
are guys who were flunkies from the
local police academy and just couldn't
make a career out of law enforcement.
And in the United States, our prisons
are almost entirely in rural areas and
they serve as the only sources of um of
jobs and thus of income for a lot of
rural white men. Well, do you know what
the qualifications are for a prison
guard in America? And I mean this quite
literally. You need a GED
and no felony convictions and that's it.
It's no wonder that they turn to
corruption and drugs and smuggling and
rape and end up committing suicide and
and beating people and abusing people
and standing by while they commit
suicide. And again, the the entire the
entire system is broken. It needs to be
scrapped and rebuilt.
Let me let me still standing on my soap
box here.
Until Ronald Reagan was elected
president,
you could go to prison in the United
States and uh with good behavior, you
could get out on federal parole. There
is no federal parole anymore thanks to
the so-called prison reform act of 1986.
Now you get five years or you get 10
years, you're doing five years or 10
years. Uh time also used to be where you
could go to prison and learn a skill.
You could learn to be a plumber or an
electrician or you could fix engines or
you know whatever. Learn how to do
whatever landscaping.
Well, they don't do any of that anymore.
So, let's say, as an example, you're
doing five years or 10 years on a drug
charge. They don't teach you how to read
and write. They don't uh they don't give
you classes so you can pass the time.
They don't give you a skill that you can
then adopt uh as a vocation when you get
out. They send you straight back to the
neighborhood that you came from. and you
are not only no better off than you were
when you went to prison, but now you
have PTSD and you're pissed off,
right?
And so what are you going to do? You're
going to do the only thing you know how
to do, and that is to sell drugs again.
When I was released, um I was released
first to a a halfway house
called Hope Village in Washington. It is
now defunct for good reason. We used to
call it abandon all hope village. There
were 220 men in this uh in this
facility. There was one, count it, there
was one job that was posted on the
bulletin board and it was to be a
dishwasher at Fudruckers and there were
220 guys beating the hell out of each
other to get that one dishwasher job
because once you had the job, you could
then transfer to your home and then have
permission to leave home to go to the
dishwasher job.
broken with a capital B.
That was the wonderful John Kuryaku.
Always love talking to him. Uh and
interesting anecdotes about Biden and
about Tucker Carlson. And you know, I'll
just say this about Tucker Carlson. I
I'm not I was talking about this with
Brad the other day. Uh I think that
I'm not interested in rehabilitating
Tucker Carlson who has said awful
things. Again, for me, it's more it's a
sad statement about the fact that you
could only find certain voices that
should have been on liberal media that
you had to go to Tucker Carlson to find
those voices or you had to find someone
uh arguing to free Assange. You couldn't
find that recently on MSNBC and that
should be a mainstream position. Um, but
uh guys, this has been a great show and
uh we are going to keep going on the
call-in. Make sure you become Patreon
supporters because
uh
uh this whole uh chat is going to be
available. If you're watching this live,
you get to see this uh whole thing with
John Kuryaku. If you're watching this
later, then you can access the show at
patreon.comthekatyhelper
show. Again, that's
patreon.comthekatyhelper show. And
you're definitely going to want to
because you'll get to hear um John
Kuryaku talking about Joe Biden, about
being on Tucker Carlson, uh about the
leaked Pentagon documents about whether
Jack Terara is a leaker or a
whistleblower. So, uh do that at
patreon.comthecatyhelper
show. again, patreon.com/thekatyhelper
show. Bye everyone. Thank you so much to
Brad, Tyler, and Phantom for the
clipping. And thank you to all of you
for coming. Bye.
Okay, calm down.
You're getting nervous, man.